Guide to the Walter Crane Drawings and Papers TAM.308
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Walter Crane Drawings and Papers
1877-1963
1877-1925
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Crane, Walter, 1845-1915
Boni, Albert, 1892-1981
TAM.308
1.5 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box and 1 oversize flat box.
Walter Crane was a British artist, illustrator, author, socialist, and leading practitioner of the Arts and Crafts movement. This collections consists of letters, postcards, illustrations, a scrapbook, and a manuscript entitled "The Architecture of Art."
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Albert Boni, April 8, 1971, who purchased these items in December 1970 from H. M. Fletcher Rare Books (London). The accession number related to this gift is 1971.009.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into one series: Papers. The series is arranged alphabetically.
Missing Title
I, Papers.
Historical/Biographical Note
Walter Crane (1845-1915) was a British artist, illustrator, author, socialist, and leading practitioner of the Arts and Crafts movement. His illustrations and political cartoons appeared widely in labor and socialist circles, including newspapers, literature, and printed ephemera. Crane also provided illustrations for fine editions of classic and contemporary literature. He also wrote on topics of art theory, including The Claims of Decorative Art (1892), in which he argued that art could not flourish in a society with an unfairly distribution of wealth.
Scope and Content Note
The Walter Crane Drawings and Papers contains letters, postcards, illustrations, a scrapbook, and a manuscript concerning Crane's artistic endeavors and socialist beliefs. Correspondence includes letters to Annie Besant, John Page Hopps, Harry Quilter, Edmund Russell, and various clients. Other materials include a poem; a memorial article; collection of socialist postcards; advertisements illustrated by Crane; a scrapbook containing several illustrated newspaper clippings; a manuscript entitled The Architecture of Art (1887); and the "Gesso Collection," a set of drawings and illustrations by Crane and others with accompanying notes concerning the use of gesso for preparing painting surfaces.
Studies (visual works); Postcards.; Scrapbooks.; Manuscripts for publication.; Drawings (visual works); Illustrations (layout features).; Advertising cards.; Socialism and art -- Great Britain.; Gesso.; Decoration and ornament, Architectural.; Arts and crafts movement |z Great Britain.; Correspondence.; Clippings (information artifacts); Russell, Edmund.; Quilter, Harry, 1851-1907; Hopps, John Page, 1834-1911; Besant, Annie, 1847-1933; Crane, Walter, 1845-1915; Boni, Albert, 1892-1981
- Series I: Papers.
  - The Architecture of Art Manuscript, ca.1887 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bases of Design: Chapter 1, circa 1902 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bases of Design: Chapter 2, circa 1902 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bases of Design: Chapter 3, circa 1902 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Bases of Design: Chapter 4, circa 1902 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bases of Design: Chapter 5, circa 1902 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Bases of Design: Chapter 7, circa 1902 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Besant, Annie: Letters to, 1887-1888, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bowers, Alfred: Letter to, Aug 15, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brown, C.and E.: Letter to, Mar 26, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Clippings containing drawings by Walter Crane, 1952-1963, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Der Triumph der Arbeit", 1891 (Flat-file-folder 4)
  - Foottit, Frederick F., 1891 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Gesso Collection: "The Dance" by Walter Crane, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Gesso Collection: Illustrations, "The Treatment of Form in Gesso Decoration", Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Gesso Collection: Illustration, "An Atlas of Astronomy" by Sir Robert Stawel Hall, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Gesso Collection: Illustration, "The Diamond Jubilee Commemoration of Her Majesty the Queen", 1897 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Gesso Collection: Illustration, "The Treatment of Form in Gesso Decoration", Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Gesso Collection: Illustration, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Gesso Collection: Illustrations, Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Gesso Collection: Notes on Gesso by Walter Crane, Feb 1893, Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Leaflet: "Children's Sunday," containing drawing by Walter Crane, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Nutt, W. D.: Letter to, Jan 4, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Postcards, Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Quilter, Harry: Letters to, 1888-1889, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Russell, Edmund: Letter to, Sep 22, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Scottish Widows' Fund Mutual Life Assurance Society Advertising Card, containing drawing by Walter Crane, Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Scrapbook: Bifolio 1: "Dear Thomas", Jun 24, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Scrapbook: Bifolio 2: Clippings containing the poem and illustration, ""To Belgium" by Walter Crane, ca.1914, Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Scrapbook: Bifolio 3: Letters and Clippings, ca.1899-1915, Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Scrapbook: Letters, 1879-1904, Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - [Sherratt] and Hughes, Messrs: Letter to, Aug 18, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Studies of Drapery, Figure, and Costume (1 of 2 folders), undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Studies of Drapery, Figure, and Costume (2 of 2 folders), undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "Vive le Commune" drawing, 1887 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Wilshire, Gaylord, Sep 30, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 25)